<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?><umich > <course subject="EECS" catalognumber="181"><name>Introduction to Computer Systems</name><prerequisite>none</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Fundamental computer skills needed to increase productivity. Use of software packages and applications including word processors, web browsers, spreadsheets, database systems. Creating a web home page. History of computing, ethics and legal issues. Introduction to basic hardware components. Intended for non CE/CS/EE majors whose goal is computer literacy.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="183"><name>Elementary Programming Concepts</name><prerequisite>none. (Credit for only one: EECS 183, Eng 101)</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Fundamental concepts and skills of programming in a high-level language. Flow of control: selection, iteration, subprograms. Data structures: strings, arrays, records, lists, tables. Algorithms using selection and iteration (decision making, fi nding maxima/minima, searching, sorting, simulation, etc.) Good program design, structure and style are emphasized. Testing and debugging. Not intended for Engineering students (who should take ENGR 101), nor for CS majors in LSA who qualify to enter EECS 280.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="203"><name>Discrete Mathematics</name><prerequisite>Math 115</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Introduction to the mathematical foundations of computer science. Topics covered include: propositional and predicate logic, set theory, function and relations, growth of functions and asymptotic notation, introduction to algorithms, elementary combinatorics and graph theory, and discrete probability theory.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="206"><name>Signals and Systems I</name><prerequisite>Math 116, Eng 101</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Introduction to theory and practice of signals and systems engineering in continuous and discrete time. Hands-on experience with representative engineering tasks in laboratory sessions involving audio, images, and other signals. Time-domain concepts: energy, power, periodicity, fi ltering, linear system, convolution, correlation, detection, modulation, sampling, quantization, histogram. Frequency-domain concepts: sinusoids, exponentials, Fourier series, Fourier transform, frequency response. Digital processing of analog signals.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="215"><name>Introduction to Circuits</name><prerequisite>Math 116, PHYS 240 (or 260), preceded or accompanied by Math 216 and EECS 206 Cannot receive credit for EECS 210 and EECS 215.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Introduction to electrical circuits. Kirchhoff’s voltage and current laws; Ohm’s law; voltage and current sources; Thevenin and Norton equivalent circuits; energy and power. Time-domain and frequency-domain analysis of RLC circuits. Operational amplifi er circuits. Basic passive and active electronic fi lters. Laboratory experience with electrical signals and circuits.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="230"><name>Electromagnetics I</name><prerequisite>Math 215, PHYS 240 (or 260) and EECS 215</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Electric charge and current. Traveling waves and phasors. Transmission lines; sinusoidal analysis and transient response. Vector calculus. Electrostatics. Magnetostatics. Laboratory segment includes experiments with transmission lines, the use of computer-simulation exercises, and classroom demonstrations.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="250"><name>Electronic Sensing Systems</name><prerequisite>preceded or accompanied by EECS 230 or Physics 240</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Introduction to properties and behavior of electromagnetic energy as it pertains to naval applications of communication, radar, and electro-optics. Additional topics include sound navigation and ranging (SONAR) tracking and guidance systems, and computer controlled systems. Several laboratory demonstrations will illustrate applications of the theories and concepts learned in the classroom.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="270"><name>Introduction to Logic Design</name><prerequisite>EECS 183 or Eng 101 or equivalent</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Binary and non-binary systems, Boolean algebra digital design techniques, logic gates, logic minimization, standard combinational circuits, sequential circuits, fl ip-fl ops, synthesis of synchronous sequential circuits, PLAs, ROMs, RAMs, arithmetic circuits, computer-aided design. Laboratory includes hardware design and CAD experiments.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="280"><name>Programming and Introductory Data Structures</name><prerequisite>Math 115 and prior programming experience.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Techniques and algorithm development and effective programming, top-down analysis, structured programming, testing, and program correctness. Program language syntax and static and runtime semantics. Scope, procedure instantiation, recursion, abstract data types, and parameter passing methods. Structured data types, pointers, linked data structures, stacks, queues, arrays, records, and trees.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="281"><name>Data Structures and Algorithms</name><prerequisite>EECS 203 and 280.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Introduction to algorithm analysis and O-notation; Fundamental data structures including lists, stacks, queues, priority queues, hash tables, binary trees, search trees, balanced trees and graphs; searching and sorting algorithms; recursive algorithms; basic graph algorithms; introduction to greedy algorithms and divide and conquer strategy. Several programming assignments.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="283"><name>Programming for Science and Engineering</name><prerequisite>EECS 183 or Eng 101 or equivalent.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Programming concepts with numeric applications for mathematics, the sciences, and engineering. Object-oriented programming, abstract data types, and standard class libraries with numeric and non-numeric applications. Elementary data structures, linked lists, and dynamic allocation. Searching and sorting methods. Not intended for CS majors.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="284"><name>Introduction to a Programming Language or System</name><prerequisite>some programming knowledge.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>1</credits><description>A minicourse covering a complex computer system or programming language. Specifi c languages or systems to be offered will be announced in advance.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="285"><name>A Programming Language or Computer System</name><prerequisite>some programming experience.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>2</credits><description>A course covering a complex computer system or programming language. Programming problems will be assigned. Specifi c languages or systems to be offered will be announced in advance.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="306"><name>Signals and Systems II</name><prerequisite>Math 216, EECS 206, and (EECS 215 or EECS 314)</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Theory and practice of signals and systems engineering in continuous and discrete time. Hands-on experience in laboratory sessions with communications, control and signal processing. Continuous-time linear systems: convolution, Fourier and Laplace transforms, transfer functions, poles and zeros, stability, sampling, introductions to communications and feedback control. Discrete-time linear systems: Z transform, fi lters, Fourier transform, signal processing. State space models of systems using fi nite-state machines.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="311"><name>Electronic Circuits</name><prerequisite>EECS 215 and EECS 320</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Circuit models for bipolar junction and fi eld-effect transistors; nonlinear elements; small-signal and piecewise analysis of nonlinear circuits; analysis and design of basic single-stage transistor amplifi ers: gain, biasing, and frequency response; digital logic circuits; memory circuits (RAM, ROM). Design projects. Lecture and laboratory.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="312"><name>Digital Integrated Circuits</name><prerequisite>EECS 215 and EECS 320</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Design and analysis of static CMOS inverters and complex combinational logic gates. Dynamic logic families, pass-transistor logic, ratioed logic families. Sequential elements (latches, fl ip-fl ops). Bipolar-based logic; ECL, BiCMOS. Memories; SRAM, DRAM, EEPROM, PLA. I/O circuits and interconnect effects. Design project(s). Lecture, recitation and software labs.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="314"><name>Circuit Analysis and Electronics</name><prerequisite>Math 216 and Physics 240. A student can receive credit for only one: EECS 210, 215, 314</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>A survey of electrical and electronic circuits for students not in EE or CE. Formulation of circuit equations; equivalent circuits; frequency response ideas; steady-state and transient response; introduction to amplifi ers; operational amplifi ers; survey of electronic devices and circuits. Use of computer simulations for analysis of more advanced circuits.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="320"><name>Introduction to Semiconductor Devices</name><prerequisite>PHYS 240 or 260</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Introduction to semiconductors in terms of atomic bonding and electron energy bands. Equilibrium statistics of electrons and holes. Carrier dynamics; continuity, drift, and diffusion currents; generation and recombination processes, including important optical processes. Introduction to: PN junctions, metalsemiconductor junctions, light detectors and emitters; bipolar junction transistors, junction and MOSFETs.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="330"><name>Electromagnetics II</name><prerequisite>EECS 230.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Time-varying electromagnetic fi elds and Maxwell’s equations. Plane-wave propagation, refl ection, and transmission. Geometric optics. Radiation and antennas. System applications of electromagnetic waves. Laboratory segment consists of experiments involving microwave and optical measurements and the design of practical systems.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="334"><name>Principles of Optics</name><prerequisite>Physics 240. A student can receive credit for only one: EECS 334 or Physics 402.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Basic principles of optics: light sources and propagation of light; geometrical optics, lenses and imaging; ray tracing and lens aberrations; interference of light waves, coherent and incoherent light beams; Fresnel and Fraunhofer diffraction. Overview of modern optics with laboratory demonstrations.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="353"><name>Introduction to Communications Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 212/316 or EECS 306.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Mathematical analysis of signals and signal processing used in analog and digital communication systems; sampling; quantization; pulse transmission; intersymbol interference; Nyquist criterion; partial response signals; eye diagrams; equalization; mixing; analog modulation and demodulation; receiver architectures; phase-locked loops; signal-to-noise ratio analysis; digital modulation and demodulation; spread spectrum communications.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="370"><name>Introduction to Computer Organization</name><prerequisite>(EECS 203 or EECS 270) and (EECS 280 or EECS 283).</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Basic concepts of computer organization and hardware. Instructions executed by a processor and how to use these instructions in simple assembly-language programs. Stored-program concept. Datapath and control for multiple implementations of a processor. Performance evaluation, pipelining, caches, virtual memory, input/output.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="373"><name>Design of Microprocessor Based Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 270 and 370 and Junior Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Principles of hardware and software microcomputer interfacing; digital logic design and implementation. Experiments with specially designed laboratory facilities. Introduction to digital development equipment and logic analyzers. Assembly language programming. Lecture and laboratory.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="376"><name>Foundations of Computer Science</name><prerequisite>EECS 203 and 280 or equivalent.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>An introduction to computation theory: fi nite automata, regular languages, pushdown automata, context-free languages, Turing machines, recursive languages and functions, and computational complexity.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="381"><name>Object Oriented and Advanced Programming</name><prerequisite>EECS 281.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Programming techniques in Standard C++ for large-scale, complex, or high-performance software. Encapsulation, automatic memory management, exceptions, generic programming with templates and function objects, Standard Library algorithms and containers. Using single and multiple inheritance and polymorphism for code reuse and extensibility; basic design idioms, patterns, and notation.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="398"><name>Special Topics</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor.</prerequisite><credits>4</credits><description>Topics of current interest selected by the faculty. Lecture, seminar, or laboratory.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="401"><name>Probabilistic Methods in Engineering</name><prerequisite>EECS 306 or 212/316 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Basic concepts of probability theory. Random variables: discrete, continuous, and conditional probability distributions; averages; independence. Introduction to discrete and continuous random processes: wide sense stationarity, correlation, spectral density.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="411"><name>Microwave Circuits I</name><prerequisite>EECS 330 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Transmission-line theory, microstrip and coplanar lines, S-parameters, signal- fl ow graphs, matching networks, directional couplers, low-pass and band-pass fi lters, diode detectors. Design, fabrication, and measurements (1-10GHz) of microwave-integrated circuits using CAD tools and network analyzers.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="413"><name>Monolithic Amplifi er Circuits</name><prerequisite>EECS 311 and EECS 320 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Analysis and design of BJT and MOS multi-transistor amplifi ers. Feedback theory and application to feedback amplifi ers. Stability considerations, polezero cancellation, root locus techniques in feedback amplifi ers. Detailed analysis and design of BJT and MOS integrated operational amplifi ers. Lectures and laboratory.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="414"><name>Introduction to MEMS</name><prerequisite>Math 215, Math 216, Physics 240 or graduate standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Micro electro mechanical systems (MEMS), devices, and technologies. Micromachining and microfabrication techniques, including planar thin-fi lm processing, silicon etching, wafer bonding, photolithography, deposition, and etching. Transduction mechanisms and modeling in different energy domains. Analysis of micromachined capacitive, piezoresistive, and thermal sensors/actuators and applications. Computer-aided design for MEMS layout, fabrication, and analysis.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="417"><name>Electrical Biophysics</name><prerequisite>EECS 206 and 215 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Electrical biophysics of nerve and muscle; electrical conduction in excitable tissue; quantitative models for nerve and muscle, including the Hodgkin Huxley equations; biopotential mapping, cardiac electrophysiology, and functional electrical stimulation; group projects. Lecture and recitation.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="420"><name>Introduction to Quantum Electronics</name><prerequisite>(EECS 320 and EECS 330 or equivalent) or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Introduction to quantum mechanics of electrons and photons. Electrons in crystals. Metals, semiconductors and insulators. Effective mass, holes, valence and conduction band. Quantum wells, wires and dots. Tunneling effects and applications. Introduction to scattering theory. Charge transport, mobilities in semiconductors. Optical absorption and gain in semiconductors. Physical phenomena discussed in this course will be related to important microelectronic devices.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="421"><name>Properties of Transistors</name><prerequisite>EECS 320 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>DC, small and large signal AC, switching and power-limiting characteristics, and derivation of equivalent circuit models of: PN junctions, metal-semiconductor and metal-insulator semiconductor diodes, bipolar junction transistors, junction and insulated-gate fi eld-effect transistors, and thyristors.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="423"><name>Solid-State Device Laboratory</name><prerequisite>EECS 320 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Semiconductor material and device fabrication and evaluation: diodes, bipolar and fi eld-effect transistors, passive components. Semiconductor processing techniques: oxidation, diffusion, deposition, etching, photolithography. Lecture and laboratory. Projects to design and simulate device fabrication sequence.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="425"><name>Integrated Microsystems Laboratory</name><prerequisite>EECS 311 or EECS 312 or EECS 414 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Development of a complete integrated microsystem, from functional defi nition to fi nal test. MEMS-based transducer design and electrical, mechanical and thermal limits. Design of MOS interface circuits. MEMS and MOS chip fabrication. Mask making, pattern transfer, oxidation, ion implantation and metallization. Packaging and testing challenges. Students work in interdisciplinary teams.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="427"><name>VLSI Design I</name><prerequisite>EECS 270 and EECS 312</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Design techniques for rapid implementations of very large-scale integrated (VLSI) circuits, MOS technology and logic. Structured design. Design rules, layout procedures. Design aids: layout, design rule checking, logic, and circuit simulation. Timing. Testability. Architectures for VLSI. Projects to develop and lay out circuits.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="429"><name>Semiconductor Optoelectronic Devices</name><prerequisite>EECS 320 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Materials for optoelectronics, optical processes in semiconductors, absorption and radiation, transition rates and carrier lifetime. Principles of LEDs, lasers, photodetectors, modulators and solar cells. Optoelectronic integrated circuits. Designs, demonstrations and projects related to optoelectronic device phenomena.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="430"><name>Radiowave Propagation and Link Design</name><prerequisite>EECS 330 and Senior Standing or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Fundamentals of electromagnetic wave propagation in the ionosphere, the troposphere, and near the Earth. Student teams will develop practical radio link designs and demonstrate critical technologies. Simple antennas, noise, diffraction, refraction, absorption, multi-path interference, and scattering are studied.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="434"><name>Principles of Photonics</name><prerequisite>EECS 330 or EECS 334 or permission of instructor or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Introduction to photonics, opto-electronics, lasers and fi ber-optics. Topics include mirrors, interferometers, modulators and propagation in waveguides and fi bers. The second half treats photons in semiconductors, including semiconductor lasers, detectors and noise effects. System applications include fi ber lightwave systems, ultra-high-peak power lasers, and display technologies.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="435"><name>Fourier Optics</name><prerequisite>EECS 211/316 or EECS 306 preceded or accompanied by EECS 334 and Junior Standing.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Basic physical optics treated from the viewpoint of Fourier analysis. Fouriertransform relations in optical systems. Theory of image formation and Fourier transformation by lenses. Frequency response of diffraction-limited and aberrated imaging systems. Coherent and incoherent light. Comparison of imagery with coherent and with incoherent light. Resolution limitations. Optical information processing, including spatial matched fi ltering.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="438"><name>Advanced Lasers and Optics Laboratory</name><prerequisite>EECS 334 or EECS 434 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Construction and design of lasers; gaussian beams; nonlinear optics; fi ber optics; detectors; dispersion; Fourier optics; spectroscopy. Project requires the design and set-up of a practical optical system.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="442"><name>Computer Vision</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Computational methods for the recovery, representation, and application of visual information. Topics from image formation, binary images, digital geometry, similarity and dissimilarity detection, matching, curve and surface fi tting, constraint propagation relaxation labeling, stereo, shading texture, object representation and recognition, dynamic scene analysis, and knowledge based techniques. Hardware, software techniques.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="451"><name>Digital Signal Processing and Analysis</name><prerequisite>EECS 212/316 or EECS 306.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Introduction to digital signal processing of continuous and discrete signals. The family of Fourier Transforms including the Discrete Fourier Transform (DFT). Development of the Fast Fourier Transform (FFT). Signal sampling and reconstruction. Design and analysis of digital fi lters. Correlation and spectral estimation. Laboratory experiences exercise and illustrate the concepts presented.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="452"><name>Digital Signal Processing Design Laboratory</name><prerequisite>(EECS 212/316 or 306) and EECS 280, or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Architectures of single-chip DSP processors. Laboratory exercises using two state-of-the-art fi xed-point processors; A/D and D/A conversion, digital waveform generators, and real-time FIR and IIR fi lters. Central to this course is a team project in real-time DSP design (including software and hardware).</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="455"><name>Digital Communication Signals and Systems</name><prerequisite>(EECS 212/316 or EECS 306) and EECS 401.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Digital transmission techniques in data communications, with application to computer and space communications; design and detection of digital signals for low error rate; forward and feedback transmission techniques; matched fi lters; modems, block and convolutional coding; Viterbi decoding.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="458"><name>Biomedical Instrumentation</name><prerequisite>EECS 215 or 314 or consent of instructor or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Measurement and analysis of biopotentials and biomedical transducer characteristics; electrical safety; applications of FETs, integrated circuits, operational amplifi ers for signal processing and computer interfacing; signal analysis and display on the laboratory minicomputer. Lectures and laboratory.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="460"><name>Control Systems Analysis and Design</name><prerequisite>EECS 212/316 or EECS 306 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Basic techniques for analysis and design of controllers applicable in any industry (e.g. automotive, aerospace, semiconductor, bioengineering, power, etc.) are discussed. Both time- and frequency-domain methods are covered. Root locus, Nyquist stability criterion, and Bode plot-based techniques are used as tools for analysis and design.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="461"><name>Embedded Control Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 306 or EECS 373 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Basic interdisciplinary concepts needed to implement a microprocessor based control system. Sensors and actuators. Quadrature decoding. Pulse width modulation. DC motors. Force feedback algorithms for human computer interaction. Real time operating systems. Networking. Use of MATLAB to model hybrid dynamical systems. Autocode generation for rapid prototyping. Lecture and laboratory.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="470"><name>Computer Architecture</name><prerequisite>EECS 370 and EECS 270, or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Basic concepts of computer architecture and organization. Computer evolution. Design methodology. Performance evaluation. Elementary queueing models. CPU architecture. Introduction sets. ALU design. Hardware and microprogrammed control. Nanoprogramming. Memory hierarchies. Virtual memory. Cache design. Input-output architectures. Interrupts and DMA. I/O processors. Parallel processing. Pipelined processors. Multiprocessors.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="477"><name>Introduction to Algorithms</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Fundamental techniques for designing effi cient algorithms and basic mathematical methods for analyzing their performance. Paradigms for algorithm design: divide-and-conquer, greedy methods, graph search techniques, dynamic programming. Design of effi cient data structures and analysis of the running time and space requirements of algorithms in the worst and average cases.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="478"><name>Logic Circuit Synthesis and Optimization</name><prerequisite>(EECS 203, EECS 270, and Senior Standing) or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Advanced design of logic circuits. Technology constraints. Theoretical foundations. Computer-aided design algorithms. Two-level and multilevel optimization of combinational circuits. Optimization of fi nite-state machines. High-level synthesis techniques: modeling, scheduling, and binding. Verifi cation and testing.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="481"><name>Software Engineering</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Pragmatic aspects of the production of software systems, dealing with structuring principles, design methodologies and informal analysis. Emphasis is given to development of large, complex software systems. A term project is usually required.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="482"><name>Introduction to Operating Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 and EECS 370 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Operating system design and implementation: multi-tasking; concurrency and synchronization; inter-process communication; deadlock; scheduling; resource allocation; memory and storage management; input-output; fi le systems; protection and security. Students write several substantial programs dealing with concurrency and synchronization in a multi-task environment, with file systems, and with memory management.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="483"><name>Compiler Construction</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Introduction to compiling techniques including parsing algorithms, semantic processing and optimization. Students implement a compiler for a substantial programming language using a compiler generating system.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="484"><name>Database Management Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Concepts and methods for the design, creation, query and management of large enterprise databases. Functions and characteristics of the leading database management systems. Query languages such as SQL, forms, embedded SQL, and application development tools. Database design, integrity, normalization, access methods, query optimization, transaction management and concurrency control and recovery.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="485"><name>Web Database and Information Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 484 or permission of instructor or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Design and use of databases in the Web context; data models, database design, replication issues, client/server systems, information retrieval, web server design; substantial project involving the development of a databasebacked web site.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="486"><name>Object-Oriented Methodology</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Object-based requirement analysis and design concepts such as program abstraction, encapsulation, polymorphism, inheritance, generalization, and reusability. Object oriented system decomposition and class design. Use of an OO Modeling and design methodology such as UML or OMT. Implementation of a software system based on OO requirement and design analysis is required.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="487"><name>Interactive Computer Graphics</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 and Senior Standing or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Computer graphics hardware, line drawing, rasterization, anti-aliasing, graphical user interface (GUI), affi ne geometry, projective geometry, geometric transformation, polygons, curves, splines, solid models, lighting and shading, image rendering, ray tracing, radiosity, hidden surface removal, texture mapping, animation, virtual reality, and scientifi c visualization.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="489"><name>Computer Networks</name><prerequisite>EECS 482 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Protocols and architectures of computer networks. Topics include client-server computing, socket programming, naming and addressing, media access protocols, routing and transport protocols, fl ow and congestion control, and other application-specifi c protocols. Emphasis is placed on understanding protocol design principles. Programming problems to explore design choices and actual implementation issues assigned.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="492"><name>Introduction to Artifi cial Intelligence</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Fundamental concepts of AI, organized around the task of building computational agents. Core topics include search, logic, representation and reasoning, automated planning, decision making under uncertainty, and machine learning.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="493"><name>User Interface Development</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Concepts and techniques for designing computer system user interfaces to be easy to learn and use, with an introduction to their implementation. Task analysis, design of functionality, display and interaction design, and usability evaluation. Interface programming using an object-oriented application framework. Fluency in a standard object-oriented programming language is assumed.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="494"><name>Computer Game Design and Development</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Concepts and methods for the design and development of computer games. Topics include: history of games, 2D graphics and animation, sprites, 3D animation, binary space partition trees, software engineering, game design, interactive fi ction, user interfaces, artifi cial intelligence, game SDK’s, networking, multi-player games, game development environments, commercialization of software.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="496"><name>Major Design Experience Professionalism</name><prerequisite>Senior Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>2</credits><description>Design principles for multidisciplinary team projects, team strategies, entrepreneurial skills, ethics, social and environmental awareness, and life long learning. Each student must take (simultaneously) Tech Comm 496 (2 cr.) and one of the approved 400-level team project courses in computing (4 cr.).</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="497"><name>EECS Major Design Projects</name><prerequisite>Senior Standing and successful completion of at least two-thirds of the credit hours required for the program subjects.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Professional problem-solving methods developed through intensive group studies. Normally one signifi cant design project is chosen for entire class requiring multiple EECS disciplines and teams. Use of analytic, computer, design, and experimental techniques where applicable are used. Projects are often interdisciplinary allowing non-EECS seniors to also take the course (consult with instructor).</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="498"><name>Special Topics</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor.</prerequisite><credits>1 4</credits><description>Topics of current interest selected by the faculty. Lecture, seminar or laboratory.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="499"><name>Directed Study</name><prerequisite>Senior Standing in EECS.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>1 4</credits><description>Individual study of selected topics in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science. May include experimental investigation or library research. Primarily for undergraduates.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="500"><name>Tutorial Lecture Series in System Science</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing; mandatory satisfactory/ unsatisfactory.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>1</credits><description>Students are introduced to the frontiers of System Science research. Sections 01, 02, and 03 are devoted, respectively, to Communications, Control, and Signal Processing. The tutorials are delivered by leaders of the respective research fi elds, invited from academia and industry. The presentations are self-contained and accessible to all graduate students in System Science.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="501"><name>Probability and Random Processes</name><prerequisite>EECS 401 or Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Introduction to probability and random processes. Topics include probability axioms, sigma algebras, random vectors, expectation, probability distributions and densities, Poisson and Wiener processes, stationary processes, autocorrelation, spectral density, effects of fi ltering, linear least-squares estimation, and convergence of random sequences. A student may receive credit for only one: EECS 401 and EECS 501.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="502"><name>Stochastic Processes</name><prerequisite>EECS 501</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Correlations and spectra. Quadratic mean calculus, including stochastic integrals and representations, wide-sense stationary processes (fi ltering, white noise, sampling, time averages, moving averages, autoregression). Renewal and regenerative processes, Markov chains, random walk and run, branching processes, Markov jump processes, uniformization, reversibility, and queueing applications.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="503"><name>Introduction to Numerical Electromagnetics</name><prerequisite>EECS 330</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Introduction to numerical methods in electromagnetics including fi nite difference, fi nite element and integral equation methods for static, harmonic and time dependent fi elds; use of commercial software for analysis and design purposes; applications to open and shielded transmission lines, antennas, cavity resonances and scattering.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="506"><name>Computing System Evaluation</name><prerequisite>EECS 183 or EECS 280, and EECS 370 and EECS 501. II odd years</prerequisite><credits>3</credits><description>Theory and application of analytic methods for evaluating the performance and reliability of computing systems. Measures of performance, reliability, and performability. Reliability evaluation: classifi cation and representation of faults, stochastic process models, coherent systems. Performance evaluation: Markovian queueing models, networks of queues. Unifi ed performance-reliability evaluation.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="509"><name>Traffi c Modeling</name><prerequisite>IOE 316, Stat 310, or EECS 401</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Traffi c Models and their analysis in the context of ITS (Intelligent Transportation Systems). Those aspects of traffi c theory relevant to ITS are presented including traffi c fl ow and signalized intersections, with particular emphasis on the optimization via route guidance and signal control of large scale traffi c networks.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="510"><name>Intelligent Transportation Systems Research Topics</name><prerequisite>two ITS-Certifi cate courses (may be taken concurrently)</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>2</credits><description>Topics include driver-highway interactions (traffi c modeling, analysis and simulation), driver-vehicle interactions (human factors), vehicle-highway interactions (computer/communications systems architecture), collision prevention, ITS technologies (in-vehicle electronic sensors, etc.), socioeconomic aspects (user acceptance and liability), and system integration (comprehensive modeling and competitive strategy).</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="512"><name>Amorphous and Microstayalline Semiconductor Thin Film Devices</name><prerequisite>EECS 421 and/or permission of instructor.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Introduction and fundamentals of physical, optical and electrical properties of amorphous and microcrystalline semiconductor based devices: MIM structures, Schottky diodes, p-i-n junctions, heterojunctions, MIS structures, thin- fi lm transistors, solar cells, threshold and memory switching devices and large area x-ray radiation detectors.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="513"><name>Flat Panel Displays</name><prerequisite>EECS 423, EECS 512 and/or permission of instructor.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Introduction and fundamentals to the passive, active, refl ective and emissive fl at panel display technologies. This course will discuss the physics, operating principles, properties and technology of the fl at panel displays.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="514"><name>Advanced MEMS Devices and Technologies</name><prerequisite>EECS 414.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Advanced micro electro mechanical systems (MEMS) devices and technologies. Transduction techniques, including piezoelectric, electrothermal, and resonant techniques. Chemical, gas, and biological sensors, microfl uidic and biomedical devices. Micromachining technologies such as laser machining and microdrilling, EDM, materials such as SiC and diamond. Sensor and actuator analysis and design through CAD.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="515"><name>Integrated Microsystems</name><prerequisite>EECS 414</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Review of interface electronics for sense and drive and their infl uence on device performance, interface standards, MEMS and circuit noise sources, packaging and assembly techniques, testing and calibration approaches, and communication in integrated microsystems. Applications, including RF MEMS, optical MEMS, bioMEMS, and microfl uidics. Design project using CAD and report preparation.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="516"><name>Medical Imaging Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 451</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Principles of modern medical imaging systems. For each modality the basic physics is described, leading to a systems model of the imager. Fundamental similarities between the imaging equations of different modalities will be stressed. Modalities covered include radiography, x-ray computed tomography (CT), NMR imaging (MRI) and real-time ultra-sound.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="517"><name>Physical Processes in Plasmas</name><prerequisite>EECS 330</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Plasma physics applied to electrical gas discharges used for material processing. Gas kinetics; atomic collisions; transport coeffi cients; drift and diffusion; sheaths; Boltzmann distribution function calculation; plasma simulation; plasma diagnostics by particle probes, spectroscopy, and electromagnetic waves; analysis of commonly used plasma tools for materials processing.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="518"><name>Magnetosphere and Solar Wind</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>General principles of magnetohydrodynamics; theory of the expanding atmospheres; properties of solar wind, interaction of solar wind with the magnetosphere of the Earth and other planets; bow shock and magnetotail, trapped particles, auroras.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="519"><name>Plasma Generation and Diagnostics Laboratory</name><prerequisite>preceded or accompanied by a course covering electromagnetism. II</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Laboratory techniques for plasma ionization and diagnosis relevant to plasma processing, propulsion, vacuum electronics, and fusion. Plasma generation includes: high voltage-DC, radio frequency, and electron beam sustained discharges. Diagnostics include: Langmuir probes, microwave cavity perturbation, microwave interferometry, laser schlieren, and optical emission spectroscopy. Plasma parameters measured are: electron/ion density and electron temperature.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="520"><name>Electronic and Optical Properties of Semiconductors</name><prerequisite>EECS 420 or EECS 540. II</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>The course discusses in detail the theory behind important semiconductorbased experiments such as Hall effect and Hall mobility measurement; velocity- fi eld measurement; photoluminescence; gain; pump-probe studies; pressure and strain-dependent studies. Theory will cover: Bandstructure in quantum wells; effect of strain on bandstructure; transport theory; Monte Carlo methods for high fi eld transport; excitons, optical absorption, luminescence and gain.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="521"><name>High-Speed Transistors</name><prerequisite>EECS 421 or EECS 422. II</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Detailed theory of high-speed digital and high-frequency analog transistors. Carrier injection and control mechanisms. Limits to miniaturization of conventional transistor concepts. Novel submicron transistors including MESFET, heterojunction and quasi-ballistic transistor concepts.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="522"><name>Analog Integrated Circuits</name><prerequisite>EECS 413</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Review of integrated circuit fabrication technologies and BJT and MOS transistor models. Detailed analysis and design of analog integrated circuits, including power amplifi ers, voltage references, voltage regulators, rectifi ers, oscillators, multipliers, mixers, phase detectors, and phase-locked loops. Design projects. Lectures and discussion.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="523"><name>Digital Integrated Technology</name><prerequisite>EECS 423 or 425 and EECS 311 and EECS 320.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Integrated circuit fabrication overview, relationships between processing choices and device performance characteristics. Long-channel device I-V review, short-channel MOSFET I-V characteristics including velocity saturation, mobility degradation, hot carriers, gate depletion. MOS device scaling strategies, silicon-on-insulator, lightly-doped drain structures, on-chip interconnect parasitics and performance. Major CMOS scaling challenges. Process and circuit simulation.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="524"><name>Field-Effect-Transistors and Microwave Monolithic Integrated Circuits Technology</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing and EECS 421, and either EECS 525 or EECS 528.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Physical and electrical properties of III-V materials, epitaxy and ion-implantation, GaAs and InP based devices (MESFETs, HEMTs varactors) and Microwave Monolithic Integrated Circuits (MMICs). Cleaning, Photolithography, metal and dielectric deposition, wet and dry etching. Device isolation, ohmic and Schottky contacts, dielectrics, passive component technology, interconnects, via holes, dicing and mounting. Study of the above processes by DC characterization.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="525"><name>Advanced Solid State Microwave Circuits</name><prerequisite>EECS 411, EECS 421 or EECS 521</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>General properties and design of linear and nonlinear solid state microwave circuits including: amplifi er gain blocks, low-noise, broadband and power amplifi ers, oscillators, mixer and multiplier circuits, packaging, system implementation for wireless communication.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="526"><name>High-Performance Dynamic Device Models and Circuits</name><prerequisite>EECS 413, or both EECS 311 and EECS 320.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Models for devices (BJTs, FETs, and integrated circuits), with primary emphasis on large-signal dynamic charge-control models. Mathematics and physics fundamentals for measurement concepts and methods. Mathematical and computer analysis and design of high-speed dynamic circuits. Dynamic circuit functional blocks, level detection/comparison circuits; sweep/ramp, multivibrator, and logic gate circuits.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="527"><name>Layout Synthesis and Optimization</name><prerequisite>EECS 478</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Theory of circuit layout partitioning and placement algorithms. Routing algorithms, parallel design automation on shared memory and distributed memory multi-processors, simulated annealing and other optimization techniques and their applications in CAD, layout transformation and compaction, fault-repair algorithms for RAMs and PLAs hardware synthesis from behavioral modeling, artificial intelligence-based CAD.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="528"><name>Principles of Microelectronics Process Technology</name><prerequisite>EECS 421, EECS 423.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Theoretical analysis of the chemistry and physics of process technologies used in micro-electronics fabrication. Topics include: semiconductor growth, material characterization, lithography tools, photo-resist models, thin fi lm deposition, chemical etching, plasma etching, electrical contact formation, microstructure processing, and process modeling.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="529"><name>Semiconductor Lasers and LEDs</name><prerequisite>EECS 429.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Optical processes in semiconductors, spontaneous emission, absorption gain, stimulated emission. Principles of light-emitting diodes, including transient effects, spectral and spatial radiation fi elds. Principles of semiconducting lasers; gain-current relationships, radiation fi elds, optical confi nement and transient effects.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="530"><name>Electromagnetic Theory I</name><prerequisite>EECS 330 or Physics 438.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Maxwell’s equations, constitutive relations and boundary conditions. Potentials and the representation of electromagnetic fi elds. Uniqueness, duality, equivalence, reciprocity and Babinet’s theorems. Plane, cylindrical, and spherical waves. Waveguides and elementary antennas. The limiting case of electro- and magneto-statics.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="531"><name>Antenna Theory and Design</name><prerequisite>EECS 330</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Theory of transmitting and receiving antennas. Reciprocity. Wire antennas: dipoles, loops and traveling-wave antennas. Analysis and synthesis of linear arrays. Phased arrays. Input impedance and method of moments. Mutual impedance. Aperture antennas: slot, Babinet’s principle. Microstrip antennas. Horns, refl ector and lens antennas.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="532"><name>Microwave Remote Sensing I: Radiometry</name><prerequisite>EECS 330, Graduate Standing</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Radiative transfer theory: blackbody radiation; microwave radiometry; atmospheric propagation and emission; radiometer receivers; surface and volume scattering and emission; applications to meteorology, oceanography, and hydrology.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="533"><name>Microwave Measurements Laboratory</name><prerequisite>EECS 330, Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Advanced topics in microwave measurements: power spectrum and noise measurement, introduction to state-of-the-art microwave test equipment, methods for measuring the dielectric constant of materials, polarimetric radar cross section measurements, near fi eld antenna pattern measurements, electromagnetic emission measurement (EM compatibility). Followed by a project that will include design, analysis, and construction of a microwave subsystem.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="534"><name>Design and Characterization of Microwave Devices and Monolithic Circuits</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing, EECS 421 or EECS 525</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Theory and design of passive and active microwave components and monolithic integrated circuits including: microstrip, lumped inductors and capacitors, GaAs FETs, varactor and mixer diodes, monolithic phase shifters, attenuators, amplifi ers and oscillators. Experimental characterization of the above components using network analyzer, spectrum analyzer, power and noise meters. Lecture and laboratory.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="535"><name>Optical Information Processing</name><prerequisite>EECS 334.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Theory of image formation with holography; applications of holography; white light interferometry; techniques for optical digital computing; special topics of current research interest.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="536"><name>Classical Statistical Optics</name><prerequisite>EECS 334 or EECS 434, and EECS 401 or Math 425.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Applications of random variables to optics; statistical properties of light waves. Coherence theory, spatial and temporal. Information retrieval; imaging through inhomogeneous media; noise processes in imaging and interferometric systems.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="537"><name>Classical Optics</name><prerequisite>EECS 330 and EECS 334</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Theory of electromagnetic, physical, and geometrical optics. Classical theory of dispersion. Linear response, Kramers-Kronig relations, and pulse propagation. Light scattering. Geometrical optics and propagation in inhomogeneous media. Dielectric waveguides. Interferometry and theory of coherence. Diffraction, Fresnel and Fraunhofer. Gaussian beams and ABCD law.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="538"><name>Optical Waves in Crystals</name><prerequisite>EECS 434</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Propagation of laser beams: Gaussian wave optics and the ABCD law. Manipulation of light by electrical, acoustical waves; crystal properties and the dielectric tensor; electro-optic, acousto-optic effects and devices. Introduction to nonlinear optics; harmonic generation, optical rectifi cation, four-wave mixing, self-focusing, and self-phase modulation.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="539"><name>Lasers</name><prerequisite>EECS 537 and EECS 538</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Complete study of laser operation: the atom-fi eld interaction; homogeneous and inhomogeneous broadening mechanisms; atomic rate equations; gain and saturation; laser oscillation; laser resonators, modes, and cavity equations; cavity modes; laser dynamics, Q-switching and modelocking. Special topics such as femto-seconds lasers and ultrahigh power lasers.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="540"><name>Applied Quantum Mechanics I</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Introduction to nonrelativistic quantum mechanics. Summary of classical mechanics, postulates of quantum mechanics and operator formalism, stationary state problems (including quantum wells, harmonic oscillator, angular momentum theory and spin, atoms and molecules, band theory in solids), time evolution, approximation methods for time independent and time dependent interactions including electromagnetic interactions, scattering.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="541"><name>Applied Quantum Mechanics II</name><prerequisite>EECS 540.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Continuation of nonrelativistic quantum mechanics. Advanced angular momentum theory, second quantization, non-relativistic quantum electrodynamics, advanced scattering theory, density matrix formalism, reservoir theory.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="542"><name>Vision Processing</name><prerequisite>EECS 442</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Details of image formation theory, including the consideration of dynamic image sequences. The theoretical frameworks for edge detection, feature extraction, and surface description are presented. The relationship between image formation and object features is examined in detail. Programming required.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="543"><name>Knowledge-Based Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 and Graduate Standing or permission of instructor. I</prerequisite><credits>3</credits><description>Techniques and principles for developing application software based on explicit representation and manipulation of domain knowledge, as applied to areas such as pattern matching, problem-solving, automated planning, and naturallanguage processing. Discussion of major programming approaches used in the design and development of knowledge-based systems.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="545"><name>Machine Learning</name><prerequisite>EECS 492</prerequisite><credits>3</credits><description>Survey of recent research on learning in artifi cial intelligence systems. Topics include learning based on examples, instructions, analogy, discovery, experimentation, observation, problem-solving and explanation. The cognitive aspects of learning will also be studied.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="546"><name>Ultrafast Optics</name><prerequisite>EECS 537</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Propagation of ultrashort optical pulses in linear and nonlinear media, and through dispersive optical elements. Laser mode-locking and ultrashort pulse generation. Chirped-pulse amplifi cation. Experimental techniques for high time resolution. Ultrafast Optoelectronics. Survey of ultrafast high fi eld interactions.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="547"><name>Electronic Commerce</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 or SI 502 or permission of instructor.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Introduction to the design and analysis of automated commerce systems, from both a technological and social perspective. Infrastructure supporting search for commerce opportunities, negotiating terms of trade, and executing transactions. Issues of security, privacy, incentives, and strategy.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="550"><name>Information Theory</name><prerequisite>EECS 501</prerequisite><credits>3</credits><description>The concepts of source, channel, rate of transmission of information. Entropy and mutual information. The noiseless coding theorem. Noisy channels; the coding theorem for fi nite state zero memory channels. Channel capacity. Error bounds. Parity check codes. Source encoding.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="551"><name>Wavelets and Time-Frequency Distribution</name><prerequisite>EECS 451</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Review of DTFT and digital fi ltering. Multirate fi ltering. Filter banks and subband decomposition of signals. Multiresolution subspaces. Wavelet scaling and basis functions and their design: Haar, Littlewood-Paley, Daubechies, Battle- Lemarie. Denoising and compression applications. Spectrogram, Wigner-Ville, Cohen’s class of time-frequency distributions and their applications.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="552"><name>Fiber Optical Communications</name><prerequisite>EECS 434 or EECS 538 or permission of instructor.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Principles of fi ber optical communications and networks. Point-to-point systems and shared medium networks. Fiber propagation including attenuation, dispersion and nonlinearities. Topics covered include erbium-doped amplifi ers, Bragg and long period gratings, fi ber transmission based on solitons and nonreturn- to-zero, and time- and wavelength-division-multiplexed networks.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="554"><name>Introduction to Digital Communication and Coding</name><prerequisite>EECS 212/316 or 306 and EECS 401.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Digital transmission of information across discrete and analog channels. Sampling; quantization; noiseless source codes for data compression: Huffman’s algorithm and entropy; block and convolutional channel codes for error correction; channel capacity; digital modulation methods: PSK, MSK, FSK, QAM; matched fi lter receivers. Performance analysis: power, bandwidth, data rate, and error probability.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="555"><name>Digital Communication Theory</name><prerequisite>EECS 501, EECS 554.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Theory of digital modulation and coding. Optimum receivers in Gaussian noise. Signal space and decision theory. Signal design. Bandwidth and dimensionality. Fundamental limits in coding and modulation. Capacity and cutoff rate. Block, convolutional and trellis coding. Continuous phase modulation. Filtered channels and intersymbol interference. Equalization. Spread-spectrum. Fading channels. Current topics.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="556"><name>Image Processing</name><prerequisite>EECS 451, EECS 501.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Theory and application of digital image processing. Random fi eld models of images. Sampling, quantization, image compression, enhancement, restoration, segmentation, shape description, reconstruction of pictures from their projections, pattern recognition. Applications include biomedical images, timevarying imagery, robotics, and optics.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="557"><name>Communication Networks</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing, preceded by EECS 401 or accompanied by EECS 501.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>System architectures. Data link control: error correction, protocol analysis, framing. Message delay: Markov processes, queuing, delays in statistical multiplexing, multiple users with reservations, limited service, priorities. Network delay: Kleinrock independence, reversibility, traffi c fl ows, throughput analysis, Jackson networks. Multiple access networks: ALOHA and splitting protocols, carrier sensing, multi-access reservations.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="558"><name>Stochastic Control</name><prerequisite>EECS 501, EECS 560</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Analysis and optimization of controlled stochastic systems. Models: linear and nonlinear stochastic controlled systems, controlled Markov chains. Optimization of systems described by Markov processes; dynamic programming under perfect and imperfect information, fi nite and infi nite horizons. System identifi cation: off-line, recursive. Stochastic adaptive control: Markov chains, self-tuning regulators, bandit problems.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="559"><name>Advanced Signal Processing</name><prerequisite>EECS 451, EECS 501</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Estimators of second order properties of random processes: nonparametric and model-based techniques of spectral estimation, characterization of output statistics for nonlinear systems, time-frequency representations. Performance evaluation using asymptotic techniques and Monte Carlo simulation. Applications include speech processing, signal extrapolation, multidimensional spectral estimation, and beamforming.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="560"><name>Linear Systems Theory</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Linear spaces and linear operators. Bases, subspaces, eigenvalues and eigenvectors, canonical forms. Linear differential and difference equations. Mathematical representations: state equations, transfer functions, impulse response, matrix fraction and polynomial descriptions. System-theoretic concepts: causality, controllability, observability, realizations, canonical decomposition, stability.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="561"><name>Design of Digital Control Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 460 or Aero 471 or ME 461.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Sampling and data reconstruction. Z-transforms and state variable descriptions of discrete-time systems. Modeling and identifi cation. Analysis and design using root locus, frequency response, and state space techniques. Linear quadratic optimal control and state estimation. Quantization and other nonlinearities. Computer simulations and laboratory implementation of realtime control systems.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="562"><name>Nonlinear Systems and Control</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Introduction to the analysis and design of nonlinear systems and nonlinear control systems. Stability analysis using Liapunov, input-output and asymptotic methods. Design of stabilizing controllers using a variety of methods: linearization, absolute stability theory, vibrational control, sliding modes and feedback linearization.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="564"><name>Estimation, Filtering, and Detection</name><prerequisite>EECS 501.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Principles of estimation, linear fi ltering and detection. Estimation: linear and nonlinear minimum mean squared error estimation, and other strategies. Linear fi ltering: Wiener and Kalman fi ltering. Detection: simple, composite, binary and multiple hypotheses. Neyman-Pearson and Bayesian approaches.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="565"><name>Linear Feedback Control Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 460 or Aero 345 or ME 461 and Aero 550 (EECS 550).</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Control design concepts for linear multivariable systems. Review of single variable systems and extensions to multivariable systems. Purpose of feedback. Sensitivity, robustness, and design tradeoffs. Design formulations using both frequency domain and state space descriptions. Pole placement/observer design. Linear quadratic Gaussian based design methods. Design problems unique to multivariable systems.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="567"><name>Introduction to Robotics: Theory and Practice</name><prerequisite>EECS 281.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Introduction to robots considered as electro-mechanical computational systems performing work on the physical world. Data structures representing kinematics and dynamics of rigid body motions and forces and controllers for achieving them. Emphasis on building and programming real robotic systems and on representing the work they are to perform.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="570"><name>Parallel Computer Architecture</name><prerequisite>EECS 470.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Architectures for explicit parallelism. Multithreaded processors, small- and large-scale multiprocessor systems. Shared-memory coherence and consistency. Effect of architecture on communication latency, bandwidth, and overhead. Latency tolerance techniques. Interconnection networks. Case studies. Term projects.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="571"><name>Principles of Real-Time Computing</name><prerequisite>EECS 470, EECS 482 or permission of instructor.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Principles of real-time computing based on high performance, ultra reliability and environmental interface. Architectures, algorithms, operating systems and applications that deal with time as the most important resource. Real-time scheduling, communications and performance evaluation.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="573"><name>Microarchitecture</name><prerequisite>EECS 470 or permission of instructor.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Graduate-level introduction to the foundations of high performance microprocessor implementation. Problems involving instruction supply, data supply, and instruction processing. Compile-time vs. run-time tradeoffs. Aggressive branch prediction. Wide-issue processors, in-order vs. out-of-order execution, instruction retirement. Case studies taken from current microprocessors.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="574"><name>Theoretical Computer Science</name><prerequisite>EECS 376</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Fundamentals of the theory of computation and complexity theory. Computability, undecidability, and logic. Relations between complexity classes, NPcompleteness, P-completeness, and randomized computation. Applications in selected areas such as cryptography, logic programming, theorem proving, approximation of optimization problems, or parallel computing.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="575"><name>Advanced Cryptography</name><prerequisite>EECS 203 or equivalent (EECS 574 recommended)</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>A rigorous introduction to the design of cryptosystems and to cryptanalysis. Topics include cryptanalysis of classical cryptosystems; theoretical analysis of one-way functions; DES and differential cryptanalysis; the RSA cryptosystem; ElGamal, elliptic, hyperelliptic and hidden mononomial cryptosystems; attacks on signature schemes, identifi cation schemes and authentication codes; secret sharing; and zero knowledge.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="577"><name>Reliable Computing Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 280 and EECS 478.</prerequisite><credits>3</credits><description>An introduction to models and methods used in the analysis and design of reliable hardware systems, software systems and computing systems. Aspects of reliability considered include fault tolerance, fault detection and diagnosis, reconfi guration, design verifi cation and testing, and reliability evaluation.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="578"><name>Computer-Aided Design Verifi cation of Digital Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 478</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Design specifi cation vs. implementation. Design errors. Functional and temporal modeling of digital systems. Simulation vs. symbolic verifi cation techniques. Functional verifi cation of combinational and sequential circuits. Topological and functional path delays; path sensitization. Timing verifi cation of combinational and sequential circuits. Clock schedule optimization.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="579"><name>Digital System Testing</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Overview of fault-tolerant computing. Fault sources and models. Testing process. Combinational circuit testing. D-Algorithm and PODEM. Sequential circuit testing. Checking experiments. RAM and microprocessor testing. Fault simulation. Design for testability. Testability measures. Self-testing circuits and systems.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="581"><name>Software Engineering Tools</name><prerequisite>EECS 481 or equivalent programming experience. II</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Fundamental areas of software engineering including life-cycle-paradigms, metrics, and tools. Information hiding architecture, modular languages, design methodologies, incremental programming, and very high level languages.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="582"><name>Advanced Operating Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 482</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Course discusses advanced topics and research issues in operating systems. Topics will be drawn from a variety of operating systems areas such as distributed systems and languages, networking, security, and protection, realtime systems, modeling and analysis, etc.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="583"><name>Advanced Compilers</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 and 370 (EECS 483 is also recommended)</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>In-depth study of compiler backend design for high-performance architectures. Topics include control-fl ow and data-fl ow analysis, optimization, instruction scheduling, register allocation. Advanced topics include memory hierarchy management, instruction-level parallelism, predicated and speculative execution. The class focus is processor-specifi c compilation techniques, thus familiarity with both computer architecture and compilers is recommended.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="584"><name>Advanced Database Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 484</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Survey of advanced topics in database systems. Distributed databases, query processing, transaction processing. Effects of data models: object-oriented and deductive databases; architectures: main-memory and parallel repositories; distributed organizations: client-server and heterogeneous systems. Basic data management for emerging areas: internet applications, OLAP, data mining. Case studies of existing systems. Group projects.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="585"><name>Web Technologies</name><prerequisite>EECS 482 or EECS 485 or permission of instructor.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Web-related client-server protocols and performance issues; web proxies; web caching and prefetching; dynamic web content; server-side web applications support; scalable web servers; security topics such as user authentication, secure sockets layer and secure HTTP; electronic payment systems; webbased virtual communities; information discovery.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="586"><name>Design and Analysis of Algorithms</name><prerequisite>EECS 281</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Design of algorithms for nonnumeric problems involving sorting, searching, scheduling, graph theory, and geometry. Design techniques such as approximation, branch-and-bound, divide-and-conquer, dynamic programming, greed, and randomization applied to polynomial and NP-hard problems. Analysis of time and space utilization.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="587"><name>Parallel Computing</name><prerequisite>EECS 281 and Graduate Standing</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>The development of programs for parallel computers. Basic concepts such as speedup, load balancing, latency, system taxonomies. Design of algorithms for idealized models. Programming on parallel systems such as shared or distributed memory machines, networks. Performance analysis. Course includes a substantial term project.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="589"><name>Advanced Computer Networks</name><prerequisite>EECS 489.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Advanced topics and research issues in computer networks. Topics include routing protocols, multicast delivery, congestion control, quality of service support, network security, pricing and accounting, and wireless access and mobile networking. Emphasis is placed on performance trade-offs in protocol and architecture designs. Readings assigned from research publications. A course project allows in-depth exploration of topics of interest.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="591"><name>Distributed Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 482 and Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Principles and practice of distributed system design. Computations, consistency semantics, and failure models. Programming paradigms including group communication, RPC, distributed shared memory, and distributed objects. Operating system kernel support; distributed system services including replication, caching, fi le system management, naming, clock synchronization, and multicast communication. Case studies.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="592"><name>Advanced Artifi cial Intelligence</name><prerequisite>EECS 492 or permission of instructor.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>4</credits><description>Advanced topics in artifi cial intelligence. Issues in knowledge representation, knowledge-based systems, problem solving, planning and other topics will be discussed. Students will work on several projects.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="594"><name>Introduction to Adaptive Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 203, Math 425 (Stat 425).</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Programs and automata that “learn” by adapting to their environment; programs that utilize genetic algorithms for learning. Samuel’s strategies, realistic neural networks, connectionist systems, classifi er systems, and related models of cognition. Artifi cial intelligence systems, such as NETL and SOAR, are examined for their impact upon machine learning and cognitive science.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="595"><name>Natural Language Processing</name><prerequisite>Senior Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>A survey of syntactic and semantic theories for natural language processing, including unifi cation-based grammars, methods of parsing, and a wide range of semantic theories from artifi cial intelligence as well as from philosophy of language. Programming will be optional, though a project will normally be required.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="596"><name>Master of Engineering Team Project</name><prerequisite>enrollment in the Masters of Engineering program in EECS. I, II, IIIa, IIIb, and III</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>1 6</credits><description>To be elected by EECS students pursuing the Master of Engineering degree. Students are expected to work in project teams, May be taken more than once up to a total of 6 credit hours.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="597"><name>Language and Information</name><prerequisite>SI 503 or EECS 281 and Graduate Standing or permission of instructor</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>A survey of techniques used in language studies and information processing. Students will learn how to explore and analyze textual data in the context of Web-based information retrieval systems. At the conclusion of the course, students will be able to work as information designers and analysts.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="598"><name>Special Topics in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor or counselor.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>1 4</credits><description>Topics of current interest in electrical engineering and computer science. Lectures, seminar, or laboratory. Can be taken more than once for credit.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="599"><name>Directed Study</name><prerequisite>prior arrangement with instructor; mandatory satisfactory/unsatisfactory.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>1 4</credits><description>Individual study of selected advanced topics in electrical engineering and computer science. May include experimental work or reading. Primarily for graduate students. To be graded on satisfactory/unsatisfactory basis ONLY.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="600"><name>Function Space Methods in System Theory</name><prerequisite>Math 419.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Introduction to the description and analysis of systems using function analytic methods. Metric spaces, normed linear spaces, Hilbert spaces, resolution spaces. Emphasis on using these concepts in systems problems.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="623"><name>Integrated Sensors and Sensing Systems</name><prerequisite>EECS 413, and either EECS 423, or EECS 425, or EECS 523</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Fundamental principles and design of integrated solid-state sensors and sensing systems. Micromachining and wafer bonding. Microstructures for the measurement of visible and infrared radiation, pressure, acceleration, temperature, gas purity, an ion concentrations. Merged process technologies for sensors and circuits. Data acquisitions circuits, microactuators and integrated microsystems.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="627"><name>VLSI Design II</name><prerequisite>EECS 427.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>4</credits><description>Advanced very large scale integrated (VLSI) circuit design. Design methodologies (architectural simulation, hardware description language design entry, silicon compilation, and verifi cation), microarchitectures, interconnect, packaging, noise sources, circuit techniques, design for testability, design rules, VLSI technologies (silicon and GaAs), and yield. Projects in chip design.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="631"><name>Electromagnetic Scattering</name><prerequisite>EECS 530 and Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Boundary conditions, fi eld representations. Low and high frequency scattering. Scattering by half plane (Wiener-Hopf method) and wedge (Maliuzhinets method); edge diffraction. Scattering by a cylinder and sphere: Watson transformation, Airy and Fock functions, creeping waves. Geometrical and physical theories of diffraction.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="632"><name>Microwave Remote Sensing II - Radar</name><prerequisite>EECS 532.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Radar equation; noise statistics; resolution techniques; calibration; synthetic aperture radar; scatterometers; scattering models; surface and volume scattering; land and oceanographic applications.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="633"><name>Numerical Methods in Electromagnetics</name><prerequisite>EECS 530.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Numerical techniques for antennas and scattering; integral representation: solutions of integral equations: method of moments, Galerkin’s technique, conjugate gradient FFT; fi nite element methods for 2-D and 3-D simulations; hybrid fi nite element/boundary integral methods; applications: wire, patch and planar arrays; scattering composite structures.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="634"><name>Nonlinear Optics</name><prerequisite>EECS 537 or EECS 538 or EECS 530.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Formalism of wave propagation in nonlinear media; susceptibility tensor; second harmonic generation and three-wave mixing; phase matching; third order nonlinearities and four-wave mixing processes; stimulated Raman and Brillouin scattering. Special topics: nonlinear optics in fi bers, including solitons and self-phase modulation.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="638"><name>Quantum Theory of Light</name><prerequisite>quantum mechanics electrodynamics and atom physics.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>The atom-fi eld interaction; density matrix; quantum theory of radiation including spontaneous emission; optical Bloch equations and theory of resonance fl uorescence; coherent pulse propagation; dressed atoms and squeezed states; special topics in nonlinear optics.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="643"><name>Theory of Neural Computation</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing or permission of instructor.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>2 4</credits><description>This course will review computational models of human cognitive processes with four goals in mind: (1) to learn about the wide variety of approaches to cognitive modeling (e.g., self-organizing nets, multi-layer nets, and backpropogation, production systems, ACT*, EPIC, Soar…) and the advantages and disadvantages of each, (2) to study some of the most important cognitive models of specifi c domains (e.g., dual task performance, reasoning, explicit learning, working memory….), (3) to evaluate when cognitive modeling is an appropriate and useful research strategy, and (4) to give students an opportunity to gain hands-on experience in implementing their own cognitive models. Students will be expected to take turns in leading discussion of specifi c papers and to work in groups in implementing a computational model.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="644"><name>Computational Modeling of Cognition</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing or permission of instructor.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>2 4</credits><description>This course will examine computational models of human cognitive processes. Course goals include learning about important computational models of specifi c cognitive domains and evaluating the appropriateness and utility of different computational approaches to substantive problems in cognition.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="650"><name>Channel Coding Theory</name><prerequisite>EECS 501 and Math 419.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>The theory of channel coding for reliable communication and computer memories. Error correcting codes; linear, cyclic and convolutional codes; encoding and decoding algorithms; performance evaluation of codes on a variety of channels.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="651"><name>Source Coding Theory</name><prerequisite>EECS 501.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Introduction to a variety of source coding techniques such as quantization, block quantization; and differential, predictive, transform and tree coding. Introduction to rate-distortion theory. Applications include speech and image coding.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="658"><name>Fast Algorithms for Signal Processing</name><prerequisite>EECS 451, EECS 501.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>2 4</credits><description>Introduction to abstract algebra with applications to problems in signal processing. Fast algorithms for short convolutions and the discrete Fourier transform; number theoretic transforms; multi-dimensional transforms and convolutions; fi lter architectures.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="659"><name>Adaptive Signal Processing</name><prerequisite>EECS 559.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>2 4</credits><description>Theory and applications of adaptive fi ltering in systems and signal processing. Iterative methods of optimization and their convergence properties: transversal fi lters; LMS (gradient) algorithms. Adaptive Kalman fi ltering and least-squares algorithms. Specialized structures for implementation: e.g., least-squares lattice fi lters, systolic arrays. Applications to detection, noise cancelling, speech processing, and beam forming.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="661"><name>Discrete Event Systems</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>2 4</credits><description>Modeling, analysis, and control of discrete event systems; untimed (logical) and timed models considered. Defi ning characteristics of discrete event systems. Logical models: languages, automata, and Petri nets. Analysis: safety, blocking, state estimation and diagnostics. Supervisory control: controllability, nonblocking and nonconfl icting languages, observability and co-observability. Timed models: timed automata and timed Petri nets. Analysis using diod algebras. Control of Petri nets. Introduction to stochastic models.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="662"><name>Advanced Nonlinear Control</name><prerequisite>EECS 562 or ME 548.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Geometric and algebraic approaches to the analysis and design of nonlinear control systems. Nonlinear controllability and observability, feedback stabilization and linearization, asymptotic observers, tracking problems, trajectory generation, zero dynamics and inverse systems, singular perturbations, and vibrational control.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="670"><name>Special Topics in Computer Architecture</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor.</prerequisite><credits>3</credits><description>Current topics of interest in computer architecture. This course may be repeated for credit.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="674"><name>Special Topics in Theoretical Computer Science</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor.</prerequisite><credits>3</credits><description>Current topics of interest in theoretical computer science. This course can be repeated for credit.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="682"><name>Special Topics in Software Systems</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor.</prerequisite><credits>3</credits><description>Current topics of interest in software systems. This course can be repeated for credit more than once.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="684"><name>Current Topics in Databases</name><prerequisite>EECS 484</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>3</credits><description>Research issues in database systems chosen for in-depth study. Selected topics such as spatial, temporal, or real-time databases; data mining, data warehousing, or other emerging applications. Readings from recent research papers. Group projects.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="692"><name>Special Topics in Artifi cial Intelligence</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor.</prerequisite><credits>3</credits><description>Current topics of interest in artifi cial intelligence. This course can be repeated for credit more than once.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="695"><name>Neural Models and Psychological Processes</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor.</prerequisite><field>II</field><credits>3</credits><description>Consideration of adaptively and biologically oriented theories of human behavior. Emphasis on both the potential breadth of application and intuitive reasonableness of various models. There is a bias toward large theories and small simulations.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="698"><name>Master’s Thesis</name><prerequisite>election of an EECS master’s thesis option.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>1 6</credits><description>To be elected by EE and EES students pursuing the master’s thesis option. May be taken more than once up to a total of 6 credit hours. To be graded on a satisfactory/unsatisfactory basis ONLY.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="699"><name>Research Work in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing, permission of instructor; mandatory satisfactory/unsatisfactory.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>1 6</credits><description>Students working under the supervision of a faculty member plan and execute a research project. A formal report must be submitted. May be taken for credit more than once up to a total of 6 credit hours. To be graded satisfactory/ unsatisfactory ONLY.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="700"><name>Special Topics in System Theory</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor (to be arranged)</prerequisite></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="720"><name>Special Topics in Solid-State Devices,Integrated Circuits, and Physical Electronics</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor.</prerequisite><credits>1 4</credits><description>Special topics of current interest in solid-state devices, integrated circuits, microwave devices, quantum devices, noise, plasmas. This course may be taken for credit more than once.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="730"><name>Special Topics in Electromagnetics</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor.(to be arranged)</prerequisite><credits>1 4</credits></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="731"><name>Space Terahertz Technology and Applications</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor; mandatory satisfactory/unsatisfactory.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>1</credits><description>Study and discussion of various topics related to high frequency applications in space exploration. Topics will be chosen from the following areas: planetary atmospheres and remote sensing, antennas, active and passive circuits, space instrumentation.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="735"><name>pecial Topics in the Optical Sciences</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing, permission of instructor (to be arranged)</prerequisite><credits>1 4</credits><description>Key topics of current research interest in ultrafast phenomena, short wavelength lasers, atomic traps, integrated optics, nonlinear optics and spectroscopy. This course may be taken for credit more than once under different instructors.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="750"><name>Special Topics in Communication and Information Theory</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor. (to be arranged)</prerequisite></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="755"><name>Special Topics in Signal Processing</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor. (to be arranged)</prerequisite><credits>1 4</credits></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="760"><name>Special Topics in Control Theory</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor. (to be arranged)</prerequisite></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="765"><name>Special Topics in Stochastic Systems and Control</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor. (to be arranged)</prerequisite><credits>3</credits><description>Advanced topics on stochastic systems such as stochastic calculus, nonlinear fi ltering, stochastic adaptive control, decentralized control, and queuing networks.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="770"><name>Special Topics in Computer Systems</name><prerequisite>permission of instructor. (to be arranged)</prerequisite></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="800"><name>Seminar in Optical Science and Engineering</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>1</credits><description>Advanced overviews of research, industrial and governmental projects not covered by the optics curriculum. Recent advances on important topics presented by renowned speakers in areas like hyperspectral imaging, laser cooling, biological manipulation, displays, laser metrology, holography and astrophysical instrumentation plus an annual site tour of local industrial optics facilities.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="820"><name>Seminar in Solid-State Electronics</name><prerequisite>Graduate Standing, permission of instructor.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>1</credits><description>Advanced graduate seminar devoted to discussing current research topics in areas of solid-state electronics. Specifi c topics vary each time the course is offered. Course may be elected more than once.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="892"><name>Seminar in Artifi cial Intelligence</name><prerequisite>EECS 592 or equivalent.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>2</credits><description>Advanced graduate seminar devoted to discussing current research papers in artifi cial intelligence. The specifi c topics vary each time the course is offered.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="990"><name>Dissertation/Pre-Candidate</name><prerequisite></prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>2 8</credits><description>Dissertation work by doctoral student not yet admitted to status as candidate. The defense of the dissertation, that is, the fi nal oral examination, must be held under a full-term candidacy enrollment.</description></course><course subject="EECS" catalognumber="995"><name>Dissertation/Candidate</name><prerequisite>Graduate School authorization for admission as a doctoral candidate.</prerequisite><field>I</field><credits>8</credits><description>Election for dissertation work by a doctoral student who has been admitted to candidate status. The defense of the dissertation, that is, the fi nal oral examination, must be held under a full-term candidacy enrollment.</description></course> </umich>